## Contact

512.632.9394 (Mobile) mmwuest@live.com

www.linkedin.com/in/ marthawuestdnp (LinkedIn)

## Top Skills

Management
Customer Service
Leadership

## Languages

English

### Certifications

NE-BC

Nurse Executive Advanced (NEA-BC)

# Martha Wuest, DNP, RN, NE-BC, NEA-BC

Nursing Administration | Nursing Director | Workforce Management | Staff Planning | Float Pool Management | Project and Program Management | IT implementations | Data analysis | Critical care | Emergency | Cath Lab.

Orlando, Florida Area

# Summary

Dedicated healthcare professional with experience as Nursing Director, Administrative Director and ACNO. Demonstrated ability to affect change through improvements in throughput, policy development, patient and staff satisfaction. Implementation of staff scheduling system in 175 hospitals.

## Experience

Orlando Health

Program Manager for Nursing & Special Projects - Workforce Applications

March 2017 - Present (3 years 5 months)

Orlando, Florida Area

#### Orlando Health

Administrative Supervisor

September 2014 - November 2016 (2 years 3 months)

#### Trident Medical Center

**Assistant CNO** 

March 2013 - June 2014 (1 year 4 months)

- Represented the Nursing and Clinical Departments in the absence of the Chief Nursing Officer.
- Assisted assigned directors to develop and control operational and capital budgets.
- Provided guidance and direction for all aspects of patient care
- Assisted in the evaluation, guidance, and continuous education of nursing & clinical personnel in all areas of the hospital.
- Participated in determining clinical and administrative goals and objectives of the Nursing and Clinical Departments.

- Lead and participated in development and/or revisions of policies, procedures, job descriptions, staffing patterns, and standards of care.
- Assisted the Nursing and Clinical Departments to comply with the most recently published standards of the Joint Commission and regulatory agencies.
- Acted as a liaison and public relations representative between the department and other organizational departments and the community.
- · Lead:
- Core team for implementation of Shared Governance model.
- Developed and lead Policy Review Committee, Rapid Admission Unit.
- Project lead for implementation of Hand Hygiene monitoring system, which resulting in increased compliance with hand hygiene
- System Director Nursing Resources and Throughput March 2013 –
   September 2013
- Direct oversight for patient throughput at Trident and Summerville campuses
- Management for:
- Float Pool
- Central Staffing Office
- Patient Placement
- Nursing Supervisors
- Inpatient Dialysis
- Infection Prevention
- Diabetes Education
- Central Equipment Management
- Vascular Access Team
- Scheduling Excellence Coach Directors, Managers, Schedulers in creation and maintenance of quality schedules, staffing grids and importance of accurate volume forecasting.
- Implemented NDNQI reporting.
- Improved patient throughput leading decrease times in discharges and ED admissions
- Implemented morning Quality Huddle for discharge planning, core measure –
   SCIP compliance and review of nursing sensitive areas.

HealthTrust Workforce Solutions (Formerly Parallon)
Director - IT&S Distributed Systems
January 2007 - January 2013 (6 years 1 month)
Sunrise, FL

• Subject matter expert. Integral part of the initial and ongoing development of the Facility Scheduler hospital staffing software.

- o Prioritization of items for development, write requirements, communication of issues.
- Exceeded expectation for implementation of Facility Scheduler in 174 HCA facilities within four years while maintaining a very high level of customer satisfaction.
- o Includes project management, development of best practices
- o Liaison between facilities and PWMS IT&S regarding all aspects of the Facility Scheduler including product demonstration, implementation, customer support.
- Work with Scheduling Excellence project for integration of all aspects of scheduling – volume forecasting, staffing matrix development, schedule quality metrics.
- Member requirements development teams for HCA ISAS project.
- Educate clients external to HCA on PWMS systems (StaffRx.net, SharePoint)
- Hired as coordinator. Promoted to Manager in 2008 and Director in 2010.

### St. David's Medical Center

Administrative Director Nursing Practice / Central Staffing Office January 2001 - January 2007 (6 years 1 month)

Austin. TX

- Developed excel applications for reporting in the Central Staffing Office (CSO) resulting in improved efficiency and productivity.
- Committee chair for continuous compliance for TJC Provision of Care Standards. Co-chair for Medication Management Standards.
- Co-chair Medication Use Team.
- Member Operations Council.
- Lead root cause analysis (RCA) for nursing related events.
- Lead Failure Mode Effects Analysis (FMEA) for Verbal/Telephone orders.
- Subject matter expert for the initial development of the HCA/PWMS Facility Scheduler, working closely with the PWMS Software Development Team.

Director of Nursing – Central Staffing Office. January 2002 – August 2004

- Work closely with House Supervisors and nursing management to assure nursing units in multiple facilities appropriately staffed.
- Interface with supplemental staffing sources to obtain qualified staff.
- Direct Float Pool of 65 nurses and technicians.
- Developed and implemented policies, processes and monitoring tools for new Staffing Effectiveness and Safe Patient Handling standards.
- Co-developed Patient Placement Center leading to streamlined patient placement.

- Chair Nursing Peer Review Committee
- Interim Director Telemetry and Intermediate Care Units.
- Continued duties listed below

Nursing Systems Coordinator. January 2001 – January 2002

- Responsible for the development, implementation and coordination of the Nursing Shared Governance model.
- Coordinate performance improvement and regulatory compliance for the Dept. of Nursing
- Chair for Patient Care Policy and Procedure and Nursing Performance Improvement committees. Member of Regulatory Standards and Disaster Planning committees.

## Education

University of North Florida

Doctor of Nursing Practice, Nursing Administration · (2015 - 2016)

University of North Florida

Doctor of Nursing Practice - Nursing Administration, Nursing Administration · (2015 - 2016)

University of Texas at Austin

Master's Degree, Nursing Administration · (1998 - 2000)